ANATOLY YAKOVENKO

aeyakovenko@gmail.com | GitHub | LinkedIn

SUMMARY

Software developer with over 10 years of experience in embedded operating systems, developing <u>patents</u>, leading projects and contributing to large groups including <u>Linux Kernel</u>, with a focus on performance and optimization for Qualcomm ARM and DSP processors.

I am a software developer with over 10 years of experience in embedded operating systems. I am an expert at embedded operating systems, debugging, power and performance optimizations. I have lead complex software projects, collaborated with large teams including Linux Kernel, and developed patents. I have a wide range of skills, from building scalable AWS RESTful servers, to implementing common subexpression elimination in a compiler. I would be a great addition to any team looking for a talented software developer that can take on any task.

SKILLS

Hardware and Systems

• Embedded Operating Systems, Linux Kernel, Android, Qualcomm MSMs, System MMUs, ARM, Hexagon DSP

Languages and Tools

• C, C++, Haskell, Lua, Make, Python, Ruby, Git, Perforce, GDB, Trace32

WORK EXPERIENCE

Qualcomm, San Diego CA

Senior Staff Engineer, 2012 to Present Staff Engineer, 2008 - 2012 Senior Engineer, 2006 - 2009 Engineer, 2003 - 2006

- Achieved 10x performance improvement in subsystem communication via FastRPC, a bridge between the DSP co-processor and ARM processor for high performance applications. Ported to Windows, Qnx, Android <u>Linux Kernel</u>. Patents: 20140136817, 20140096148
- 2.5x reduction in power porting ARM/Neon Image Processing algorithms to DSP
- IDL (Interface Description Language) compiler for <u>Hexagon SDK</u>
- Dynamic linker for loading dynamic processes on Qualcomm's embedded DSP OS
- Dynamic module framework for loading shared objects on DSP from the application processor
- Capability based application framework for BREW (Qualcomm's Mobile Operating System)
- Component Object Model IPC (Inter-Process Communication) implementation for BREW
- IDL compiler with C/C++/Lua backends for BREW IPC
- Elf manipulator with a DSL (Domain Specific Language) in Lua

- System call trace tool for BREW IPC with a Lua DSL.
- Build system plugins for unit testing and verifying code coverage
- Declarative full featured object library for C with C++ compatible v-tables, in less then 500 bytes of RO arm object code
- Prototype and test generation tool for rapid development of BREW components
- Network components using SIP/HTTP/RTP and proprietary standards for QChat push to talk service
- High performance logging tools to handle tens of thousands of transactions per second from many networked components

Alescere LLC, Lisle IL

Co-Founder, 2001 to 2003

- Founding member of Alescere, a VOIP startup
- SIP and <u>RTP</u> protocol stacks, and server components for a VoIP system for small businesses

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Research Assistant, 2003

- Web server that supports QoS for HTTP requests
- Probabilistic scheduler for the Linux kernel
- Roaming protocol for 802.11a/b networks for NetBSD

Personal Research

 Neural Networks, Genetic Algorithms, Markov Models, and Bayesian Inference Algorithms

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 2003